This video shows
how to get pictures from Picasa
though its REST API and XML feed.
Then how to build both a desktop application
and a web page served by Pharo itself
to display them.
The main (World) menu is opened
by clicking on the background.
For more readability
I increase the font size
through the Settings Browser.
Picasa provides a RESTful API
through which we can search for photos
and get the result as a XML document.
Just copy the provided URL
and paste it into a Pharo workspace.
A workspace is used to dynamically evaluate some Smalltalk code.
Let's search for five photos of lighthouses.
ZnClient allows to build, execute and process HTTP requests
The XML feed is successfully retrieved
but it's not easy to examine it as a raw string.
Pharo doesn't come with a XML parser,
but we can install one easily thanks to the Configuration Browser.
Configuration Browser allows to install Metacello configurations,
which describe groups of packages and their dependencies
for each version of Pharo.
Once done, the XMLDOMParser class is loaded into Pharo
and we can use it to parse the XML feed.
Pharo comes with awesome debugging tools.
Using the Explorer, we can browse the entire object graph
which makes it easy to inspect the hierarchy of XML nodes !
Each photo is described in an entry tag
wich itself contains a self-explaining title tag
and the URL in the src attribute of a content tag
From the inspector you can access the class of every object
using the Browse Class menu entry.
The default class browser is named Nautilus.
It offers a large range of tools to browse and modify classes.
We can dynamically evaluate some Smalltalk code
in the context of the explorer.
From the root node of the XML document
we can retrieve all children nodes
that are named entry.